Guide to the Arthur Row Collection relating to Sarah Bernhardt, 1913-1921 CTC.1989.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Arthur Row Collection relating to Sarah Bernhardt
1913-1921
CTC.1989.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
2.0 linear feet (5 boxes)
Arthur Row was involved in theatre as an actor, a producer, and a journalist. He was also the press representative for Madame Sarah Bernhardt's 1916-17 'Farewell' American tour. This collection contains photographs, correspondence, press releases, scrapbooks, and magazine articles that Row amassed from his own career and during his time under Bernhardt's employment.
Row, Arthur William, 1878-1961
Biography
Arthur William Row was a professional actor, writer, and producer with a lengthy career in the theater. Throughout his career, he associated himself with many legendary performers of the 19th and early 20th centuries. He was born in Montreal, Canada on June 12, 1878 and moved with his family to Boston in 1893. Row attended Tufts College in Massachusetts from 1897 to 1901, majoring in English, with the intention of becoming a writer. During college, he decided instead to become an actor and applied to Boston's Castle Square Theatre Stock Company.
Row achieved his first major production role in 1899 in Minnie Maddern Fiske's Becky Sharp. From that point forward, he was heavily involved with the theatre and performed with the Barrymores, Herbert Beerbohm Tree, Otis Skinner, and in more modern productions such as Orson Welles' 1937 production of Julius Caesar, and A Streetcar Named Desire with Uta Hagen. In 1919, Row helped found the Afternoon Theatre and produced several plays, most notably Aglavaine and Selysette starring Eva Le Gallienne.
Arthur Row's association with Sarah Bernhardt began in 1913 when he wrote an article about her for The New Age. Bernhardt enjoyed the piece and invited Row to meet her. Three years later, Bernhardt's manager William F. Connor asked Row to be the press representative for Madame Sarah's 1916-17 'Farewell' American tour. He published a great many articles about her and continued to do so after the tour was finished. He wrote a series called 'Memories of Sarah Bernhardt' for The Younger Set magazine and in the late 1940's wrote a book titled Sarah The Divine.
Arthur Row died in 1961.
For more detailed information about Row, consult:
Personal file of Arthur Row clippings. (Courtesy of New York Public Library) In Curtis Vertical File.
For more information about Sarah Bernhardt, consult:
The Oxford Companion to the Theatre. PN2102 H333
Skinner, Cornelia Otis. Madame Sarah. PN2638 B5S62.
Aston, Elaine. Sarah Bernhardt: a French Actress on the English Stage. PN2638 B5A77 1989.
Nadar, Felix. Sarah Bernhardt vue par les Nadar. Curtis Collection. fPN2638 B5N32 1982.
Arrangement
The collection has been divided into three separate sets of series to facilitate indexing. Additional scope and content notes are found at the series level.
Series I. Sarah Bernhardt
Series II. Arthur Row
Series III. Scrapbooks
Scope and Content Notes
Due to preservation concerns, most of the material in this collection has been photocopied onto acid-free paper - notably the scrapbooks in Series III. The original items have been housed seperately. If you would like to see original pieces, please ask the Curator of the Curtis Theatre Collection.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Received as gift collection prior to 1990.
Previous Citation
Arthur Row Collection relating to Sarah Bernhardt, CTC.1989.01, Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Arthur Row Collection relating to Sarah Bernhardt, CTC.27, Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Bernhardt, Sarah, 1844-1923; Row, Arthur William, 1878-1961; Actresses -- United States; Performing arts -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Theater; Theater -- United States
- Sarah Bernhardt, I.
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I contains materials pertaining to Sarah Bernhardt that Row either produced or compiled throughout his years of working with her. Folders 1-7 contain Bernhardt typescripts (ca. 1913-1921). The typescripts represent a selection of Row's articles about Sarah Bernhardt and many contain marginalia with author notes and corrections that range from his account of his first meeting with Bernhardt to articles written while he was in her employ, and later reminisences of the actress. Folders 8-19 include press releases(c.1913)comprised of proofs of human-interest articles on a variety of topics written by Sarah Berhnhardt for syndication to U.S. newspapers during her American tour of 1913. Lastly, folders 20-23 contains newspaper clippings, a photograph of Bernhardt, a program for the 1916-17 tour, and a note handwritten by Bernhardt on her stationary.
  - Biographical Material, ca. 1913-1921 (Box 1, Folder 1-7)
  - June-July 1913 (Folder 8-19)
  - Program, American Tour, 1916-1917 (Folder 20)
  - Photograph (Bernhardt with great-grandchildren), 1916 (Folder 21)
  - Clippings, ca. 1910 (Folder 22)
  - Letter from Bernhardt to Madame Rejane, not dated (Folder 23)
- Arthur Row, II.
  Series II consists of all material not directly related to Bernhardt. The first group of materials in Series II comprises Arthur Row's collection of photographs (some of which are autographed) featuring various people related to the theatre including Herbert Beerbohm Tree, the Barrymores, etc. Folders 1-35 contains coorrespondence(c.1913-1922)to Row from various individuals, including Eva La Gallienne, Ethel Barrymore, etc. Some authors are unknown. Finally, Folders 36-45 includes miscellaneous items such as typescripts of other writings by Row, playscripts, programs, theatre-related clippings, and a 1931 issue of Livingston's International Casting Directory, featuring Row and other actors, film studio personnel, etc..
  - Barrymores (Folder 24)
  - Braley, Burton (S) (Folder 25)
  - Collier, Constance (Folder 26)
  - Gauthier, Eva (S) (Folder 27)
  - Harcourt, Cyril (Folder 28)
  - Richardson, Constance Stewart (S) (Folder 29)
  - Row, Arthur [3] (Folder 30)
  - Tree, Herbert Beerbohm [2] (S) (Folder 31)
  - Van Dresser, Marcia (S) (Folder 32)
  - Watson, Leona (S) (Folder 33)
  - unidentified [5] (Folder 34)
  - n.a., 1913 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - n.a., 1/22/1915 (Folder 2)
  - Aldridge, Lewis, 6/9/1915 (Folder 3)
  - Rives, Amelie (aka Princess Amelie Troubetzkoy), 5/2/1916 (Folder 4)
  - n.a., 1/1917 (Folder 5)
  - n.a., 1/10/1917 (Folder 6)
  - Hull, Josephine, 4/6/1918 (Folder 7)
  - 2nd Church of Christ, Scientist. New York, NY, 12/4/1918 (Folder 8)
  - n.a., 3/2/1919 (Folder 9)
  - Barrymore, Ethel, 3/25/19 (Folder 10)
  - Edjett, Edwin F., 11/6/1919 (Folder 11)
  - Matthison, Edith, 2/23/1920 (Folder 12)
  - n.a., 6/3/1920 (Folder 13)
  - Carmichael, Leonard, 5/12/1921 (Folder 14)
  - Comstock, Elinor, 7/2/1921 (Folder 15)
  - Row, Arthur (to Leonard Carmichael), 7/8/1921 (Folder 16)
  - Le Gallienne, Eva, 11/1921 (Folder 17)
  - Brown, Charles, 11/22/1921 (Folder 18)
  - n.a., 11/22/1921 (Folder 19-20)
  - Comstock, Elinor, 11/23/1921 (Folder 21)
  - Gillmore, Frank. Actor's Equity, 11/25/1921 (Folder 22)
  - Riggs, Francis Behn. Riggs School Inc., 12/16/1921 (Folder 23)
  - n.a., 1/1/1922 (Folder 24)
  - Arthur, Helen, 1/4/1922 (Folder 25)
  - Potter, Grace, 1/9/1922 (Folder 26)
  - Brown, Chamberlain (Folder 27)
  - Comstock, Elinor (2) (Folder 28)
  - Hull, Josephine (Folder 29)
  - Ivan, Rosalind (Folder 30)
  - Kamm, Philip Schuyler (Folder 31)
  - Richardson, Constance Stewart (Folder 32)
  - Theta Delta Chi fraternity (Folder 33)
  - Trader, Gertrude (Folder 34)
  - 18 Unidentified Letters (Folder 35)
  - Program: Milestones, with A. Row, 1914 (Folder 36)
  - Clippings, ca. 1914-1921 (Folder 37)
  - Playscript: Aglavaine Selysette by Maurice Maeterlinck, with notes by Row. 49pp. (Folder 38)
  - Playscript (partial): Therese Raquin by Emile Zola, with notes by Row. 21pp. (Folder 39)
  - Publications of the National Musical League of America/National Opera Companies. (2) (Folder 40)
  - 41 Typescript (partial): How a Folk Play is Produced, article by Row. 1p. (Folder 41)
  - Typescript: The Red Lights or the White Life, article by Row. 7pp. (Folder 42)
  - Typescript: Under Orders, play review by Row. 2pp. (Folder 43)
  - Typescript: Home - As the Root of All Evil article by Row. 4pp. (Folder 44)
  - Livingston's International Casting Directory, 144pp., Oct., 1931. (Folder 45)
- Scrapbooks, III.
  These three scrapbooks, compiled by Row, contain both general theatre material and Bernhardt material in the form of clippings, programs, and correspondence from Bernhardt's manager, William Connor, and others.
  - Chiefly Bernhardt, ca. 1910-1917 (Volume 1-2)
  - General Theatre Material, ca. 1896-1905 (Volume 3)